<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Keksipurkki</title>
    <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Keksipurkki</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>🍪 0x44FC6000 &#39;til 0x7FF0000000000000 Elias A. Toivanen — All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Exploring probability theory with Apache Kafka</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/kafka-clt-09-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/kafka-clt-09-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I can still remember the moment when I created a&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/rfCNsBHLDeY&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; profile. The act felt almost defiant as&#xA;it meant that I was going to leave the sheltered student life behind me. Little&#xA;did I know that ten years from that moment I would be writing a blog about the&#xA;event broker system powering the social media platform, and then creating an&#xA;event about it on the very same platform. Neither did I know that the system in&#xA;question had the name &lt;a href=&#34;https://kafka.apache.org/&#34;&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/a&gt; or that it would&#xA;such a success story among technology companies after its inception at LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting to Deploy: Negotiating A Sprint Without Giving In</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/getting-to-deploy-06-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/getting-to-deploy-06-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;December 2023 was a big one for me. I completed a project at work I have been&#xA;working on for the last 3 years. What I did and what the project was about is&#xA;doubly-irrelevant for this blog. For the first, in my line of business one is&#xA;not supposed to talk shop in the public. For the second, I ultimately do not&#xA;care.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure style=&#34;float:right; width:50%; margin-right: 0.25em;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;img alt=&#34;Pyramid and UFOs&#34; src=&#34;https://www.keksipurkki.net/pyramid_ufos.png&#34; /&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;At least some of the ways of working of ancient Egyptians&#xA;  seem alien to us.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I argue that the biggest blunder of my generation is to insist that work should&#xA;have some deep fulfilling meaning. I think this is asking too much. For the&#xA;purposes of one&amp;rsquo;s mental health, it is sufficient that it make some sense most&#xA;of the time. Just think about the pyramids in Egypt. They look miraculous not&#xA;only as physical objects but also as reminders of the work of countless hordes&#xA;of people. Yet, at least I struggle to find any meaning in them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flags of the world apart</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/svd-12-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/svd-12-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Memorizing the flags of the world is a good exercise for your brain. What kind of&#xA;strategy would you use? I have noticed that grouping the flags by visual&#xA;similarity helps me, which made me think about the topic from a programmer&amp;rsquo;s point&#xA;of view. I ended up jacking code from the 1970&amp;rsquo;s which rekindled my long&#xA;forgotten passion for numerical linear algebra and got me cursing the&#xA;Taliban regime of Afghanistan for messing with my principal component analysis&#xA;code.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JSON lines for fun and profit</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/logback-08-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/logback-08-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Observability is one of the concepts attached to modern cloud&#xA;native applications. Applications logs are arguably the most important aspect of&#xA;it. In this blog post I want to show you a variation of my current setup in the&#xA;hope that it gives you ideas on how to pimp up your own applications as well.&#xA;Reader discretion is advised as this blog contains vanilla Java code listings&#xA;which some people might find disturbing.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>API Conference 2023 London</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/2023-04-api-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/2023-04-api-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I put on my monocle and top hat and booked a ticket to London to attend my first&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://apiconference.net/app&#34;&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt;. The topic of the conference was&#xA;APIs, i.e. the stuff I develop and design at work. The trip took place in late&#xA;April 2023 under the auspices of my employer, OP Financial Group. I attended a&#xA;dozen or so lectures. What follows are the highlights of three of them.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On programming well</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/better-code-nov-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/better-code-nov-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  I was at my colleague&amp;rsquo;s housewarming party not so long time ago. After some&#xA;sauna and refreshments the discussion turned to — surprise, surprise —&#xA;programming. One of the guests opined that understanding data is all there is to&#xA;programming. I nodded my head. After pondering about it for a while, I came up&#xA;with this blog. Enjoy!&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-is-king&#34;&gt;Data is king&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure style=&#34;float:right; width:40%; margin-right: 0.25em;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;img alt=&#34;Red green and blue&#34; src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/42/LED_Display_under_microscope.png&#34; /&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;The light-emitting diodes of a display under a microscope.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although I could describe my work by saying that I write code, the end result&#xA;does not somehow really even matter compared to the data the code processes.&#xA;There is a fundamental duality between code and data. Code is either correct or&#xA;incorrect — black and white so to speak. Data on the other hand is very colorful&#xA;and often beautiful. Sometimes quite literally. When seen as data, an image is&#xA;nothing else than a collection of intensity values for the red, green and blue&#xA;diodes for a display.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scrum: Stages of Grief</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/scrum-08-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/scrum-08-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scrum is a methodology to organize team work. Created by &lt;strong&gt;Jeff Sutherland&lt;/strong&gt; and&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Ken Schwaber&lt;/strong&gt; in the early 1990s, it is a perfect example of combining tried&#xA;and true ideas from the Orient and the Occident until you arrive at something&#xA;novel. In the case of Scrum, the problem it sought to initially solve is how to&#xA;develop enterprise software in a way that actually creates value to end users.&#xA;Since its initial conception, the methodology has been recognized to be&#xA;applicable to just about any human endeavour that requires both creativity and&#xA;team work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What cloud native should mean</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/cloud-native/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/cloud-native/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Cloud native is one of the buzzwords tossed around in the developer world. What&#xA;does the term mean? Here&amp;rsquo;s my take on what it should mean. Worst comes to worst,&#xA;you still want to a develop an application that can be run end-to-end on your&#xA;own machine?&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure style=&#34;float:right; width:45%; margin-right: 0.25em;&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;img  alt=&#34;Cloud native&#34; src=&#34;https://www.keksipurkki.net/cloud_native.png&#34; /&gt;&#xA;  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;small&gt;A cloud native startup in the 2010s.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I first encountered the term &lt;em&gt;cloud native&lt;/em&gt; when I saw a cartoon contrasting the&#xA;arduous journey of an enterprise migrating to a cloud platform versus a cloud&#xA;native startup for which deploying changes to production is merely a matter of&#xA;executing &lt;code&gt;heroku deploy&lt;/code&gt;. I associated the term with &amp;ldquo;digital native,&amp;rdquo; which in&#xA;turn made me think about all the legacy concepts I still cling on to. To think&#xA;that some developers nowadays have not ever used a rotary dial telephone! Do they&#xA;even &lt;code&gt;listen(2)&lt;/code&gt; anymore?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do you need maths to be a software developer?</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/maths-and-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/maths-and-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;would-it-be-time-to-give-maths-a-second-chance&#34;&gt;Would it be time to give maths a second chance?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every now and then I come across social media campaigns and the like that aim to&#xA;inspire non-techies to take on programming. While I praise their goal, these&#xA;campaigns tend to have one thing in common that makes me cringe. They try to be&#xA;inclusive at the cost perpetuating a misguided image of the role of maths in&#xA;software development. The sentiment is that you do not need maths to become a&#xA;software developer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Musings about JSON and jq</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/jq-march-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/jq-march-21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Oh, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7159&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.json.org/json-en.html&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-C-JoyNuQJs&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;…what would the world&#xA;be without you? Let me show you what I have learned recently about this&#xA;ubiquitous data-interchange format. It turns out you can manipulate complex JSON&#xA;strings on the command line with ease. This came to me as somewhat of a surprise&#xA;as I always thought that JSON is fundamentally incompatible with traditional&#xA;command line tools, the Unix filters &lt;em&gt;cat&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;grep&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sed&lt;/em&gt; and friends, that&#xA;operate on &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; structured text files in a line-oriented fashion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top reads of 2019: Juha Hurme — Niemi (2017)</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/2019-books-pt1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/2019-books-pt1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New year, new gear. Time to reflect on the lessons learned during 2019, a year&#xA;that I remember from its warm and pleasant summer, Greta Thunberg and climate&#xA;anxiety, Brexit drama, and the &amp;ldquo;stable genius&amp;rdquo; of Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, one of the highlights of the year was that I left Europe for&#xA;the first time for a summer holiday in California, USA. I traveled alone, even&#xA;though a travel companion or an entourage of such would have been nice. Luckily&#xA;there&amp;rsquo;s one thing a solo traveller can do at their leisure that&amp;rsquo;s not so&#xA;convenient when travelling in company. And that is to binge-read books 🤓.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vim - Vi IMproved, a programmer&#39;s text editor</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/vim-oct-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/vim-oct-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Vim has been my editor of choice from day one, and I have been using the same&#xA;setup for years. I pimped up my Vim to match what&amp;rsquo;s possible in October 2019.&#xA;Here are my thoughts about coding editors and a breakdown of my setup.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My first stab at programming was writing shell scripts for fun. I started by&#xA;watching a video course on the topic. I would not know the name nor the&#xA;publisher of this course anymore. All I can say is that the resolution of the&#xA;videos would not meet the requirements of our 4k era where everything is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=napDjGFjHR0&#34;&gt;fun and&#xA;games&lt;/a&gt;. But I can still vividly&#xA;remember that the lecturer, an elderly gentleman, had a soothing voice and used&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vim.org&#34;&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; over PuTTY to write his scripts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Redux/ReactJS app done right</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-redux-types/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-redux-types/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  There has been a lot of developer buzz around TypeScript, ReactJS and Redux for&#xA;many years already and the interest does not shows signs of subsiding. Here are&#xA;my reflections on the lessons learned on writing type-safe and deterministic&#xA;applications with the combo. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://demo.keksipurkki.net&#34;&gt;demo app&lt;/a&gt; and its&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/keksipurkki/notes&#34;&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt; are provided.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I will show you how you can implement a strongly-typed&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://redux.js.org&#34;&gt;Redux/ReactJS app&lt;/a&gt; in&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.typescriptlang.org&#34;&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt; with the bare minimum of&#xA;type-annotations and external dependencies. The only requirement is that we will&#xA;be using TypeScript version 2.8 or higher.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunnelvision</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/tunnelvision/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/tunnelvision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  SSH reverse port forwarding is a technique that powers services that let you&#xA;instantly share any server application on your LAN to the public Internet. After realizing&#xA;that these services are not so secure as you might think, I decided to roll my&#xA;own tunnelling service by the name of &lt;a href=&#34;https://tunnelvision.me&#34;&gt;Tunnelvision&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be awesome to instantly show the web application you are developing from your&#xA;local machine to the rest of the world? You know, just as a sneak preview without going&#xA;through the motions of a full deployment. Or perhaps you are developing a server and a&#xA;mobile app at the same time, and the two cannot talk to each other because they are not on&#xA;the same &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>N-dimensional arrays</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-ndarray/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 09:04:43 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-ndarray/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ah, the joy of number crunching in an inefficient interpreted language in the&#xA;heat of the summer. But I got a severe flashback from my student days and&#xA;started to think about my old love &lt;a href=&#34;https://numpy.org&#34;&gt;NumPy&lt;/a&gt; and whether or not&#xA;N-dimensional arrays could also work in JavaScript.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a little something I&amp;rsquo;ve been musing over as of late. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing around with&#xA;N-dimensional arrays in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.typescriptlang.org&#34;&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt;. These are objects&#xA;that generalize vectors and matrices and typically store numbers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
