<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Development on Keksipurkki</title>
    <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/tags/development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Development on Keksipurkki</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>🍪 0x44FC6000 &#39;til 0x7FF0000000000000 Elias A. Toivanen — All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.keksipurkki.net/tags/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Musings about JSON and jq</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/jq-march-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/jq-march-21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Oh, &lt;a href=&#34;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7159&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.json.org/json-en.html&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-C-JoyNuQJs&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;…what would the world&#xA;be without you? Let me show you what I have learned recently about this&#xA;ubiquitous data-interchange format. It turns out you can manipulate complex JSON&#xA;strings on the command line with ease. This came to me as somewhat of a surprise&#xA;as I always thought that JSON is fundamentally incompatible with traditional&#xA;command line tools, the Unix filters &lt;em&gt;cat&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;grep&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sed&lt;/em&gt; and friends, that&#xA;operate on &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; structured text files in a line-oriented fashion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vim - Vi IMproved, a programmer&#39;s text editor</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/vim-oct-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/vim-oct-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Vim has been my editor of choice from day one, and I have been using the same&#xA;setup for years. I pimped up my Vim to match what&amp;rsquo;s possible in October 2019.&#xA;Here are my thoughts about coding editors and a breakdown of my setup.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My first stab at programming was writing shell scripts for fun. I started by&#xA;watching a video course on the topic. I would not know the name nor the&#xA;publisher of this course anymore. All I can say is that the resolution of the&#xA;videos would not meet the requirements of our 4k era where everything is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=napDjGFjHR0&#34;&gt;fun and&#xA;games&lt;/a&gt;. But I can still vividly&#xA;remember that the lecturer, an elderly gentleman, had a soothing voice and used&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vim.org&#34;&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; over PuTTY to write his scripts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Redux/ReactJS app done right</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-redux-types/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-redux-types/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  There has been a lot of developer buzz around TypeScript, ReactJS and Redux for&#xA;many years already and the interest does not shows signs of subsiding. Here are&#xA;my reflections on the lessons learned on writing type-safe and deterministic&#xA;applications with the combo. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://demo.keksipurkki.net&#34;&gt;demo app&lt;/a&gt; and its&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/keksipurkki/notes&#34;&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt; are provided.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I will show you how you can implement a strongly-typed&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://redux.js.org&#34;&gt;Redux/ReactJS app&lt;/a&gt; in&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.typescriptlang.org&#34;&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt; with the bare minimum of&#xA;type-annotations and external dependencies. The only requirement is that we will&#xA;be using TypeScript version 2.8 or higher.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunnelvision</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/tunnelvision/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/tunnelvision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  SSH reverse port forwarding is a technique that powers services that let you&#xA;instantly share any server application on your LAN to the public Internet. After realizing&#xA;that these services are not so secure as you might think, I decided to roll my&#xA;own tunnelling service by the name of &lt;a href=&#34;https://tunnelvision.me&#34;&gt;Tunnelvision&lt;/a&gt;.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be awesome to instantly show the web application you are developing from your&#xA;local machine to the rest of the world? You know, just as a sneak preview without going&#xA;through the motions of a full deployment. Or perhaps you are developing a server and a&#xA;mobile app at the same time, and the two cannot talk to each other because they are not on&#xA;the same &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>N-dimensional arrays</title>
      <link>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-ndarray/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 09:04:43 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.keksipurkki.net/posts/typescript-ndarray/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p class=&#34;pa2 mw7 f6 lh-copy i&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Ah, the joy of number crunching in an inefficient interpreted language in the&#xA;heat of the summer. But I got a severe flashback from my student days and&#xA;started to think about my old love &lt;a href=&#34;https://numpy.org&#34;&gt;NumPy&lt;/a&gt; and whether or not&#xA;N-dimensional arrays could also work in JavaScript.&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a little something I&amp;rsquo;ve been musing over as of late. I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing around with&#xA;N-dimensional arrays in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.typescriptlang.org&#34;&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt;. These are objects&#xA;that generalize vectors and matrices and typically store numbers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
